<Document>
  # Rules

  ## Core Rules

  These rules apply at all times, including between rounds.

  - [textlink="1. Admins have final say" link="RuleC1"]
  - [textlink="2. Don't be a dick" link="RuleC2"]
  - [textlink="3. No sexual content/themes, including erotic roleplay (ERP) and no shock content" link="RuleC4"]
  - [textlink="4. Do not use out of game methods to communicate with other players" link="RuleC5"]
  - [textlink="5. Do not attempt to evade bans" link="RuleC6"]
  - [textlink="6. Use mostly English" link="RuleC7"]
  - [textlink="7. Do not exploit the game, use cheats, or macros" link="RuleC8"]
  - [textlink="8. Do not use multiple accounts, or alt accounts, and do not share accounts" link="RuleC9"]
  - [textlink="9. Do not abuse or ignore admin messages" link="RuleC10"]
  - [textlink="10. Do not threaten to ahelp other players or argue with them about rules" link="RuleC11"]
  - [textlink="11. Players must be and act at least 16 years old" link="RuleC12"]
  - [textlink="12. Use realistic character names" link="RuleC13"]
  - [textlink="13. Do not use LOOC or OOC to share current round information" link="RuleC14"]

  ## Roleplay Rules

  These rules only apply during a round. A round ends only when the round summary has appeared. All of these rules apply fully until the moment that the round summary appears, even while the arrivals shuttle is in transit.

  The deathmatch and sandbox game modes are exempt from these rules. Players who choose to not follow these rules are entirely responsible for knowing if an exempt game mode is active.

  Roleplay rules do not apply to ghosts/spectators/observers while they are ghosts/spectators/observers. Dead chat is considered to be an in-game out of character chat channel.

  See the list of [textlink="role types" link="RoleTypes"] for more information about the different types of roles.

  - [textlink="1. Roleplay a normal person" link="RuleR3"]
  - [textlink="2. Do not metagame, obey the Metashield" link="RuleR4"]
  - [textlink="3. Do not stall the round" link="RuleR7"]
  - [textlink="4. As a member of a team, only be friendly to your team and don't work against your team" link="RuleR8"]
  - [textlink="5. As a member of a team, do not cause excessive death, damage, or destruction beyond your objectives" link="RuleR9"]
  - [textlink="6. Listen to your team leader" link="RuleR10"]
  - [textlink="7. Follow reasonable escalation" link="RuleR11"]
  - [textlink="8. Do not abandon your role" link="RuleR12"]
  - [textlink="9. Stick to your role" link="RuleR13"]
</Document>
