<Document>
# Medical

In the Stone age, most of the medicine you will find is restricted to bandages and medicinal herbs.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GauzeLeather" /> You can craft bandages from [bold]cloth[/bold] and [bold]leather[/bold]. They will help you stop bleeding.

You can find medicinal herbs growing wild around the map. If you harvest them, you will also get some seeds so you can plant them yourself.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="WildPlantElderflower" /><GuideEntityEmbed Entity="ElderflowerHealingHerbs" />
[bold]Elderflower[/bold] has a long history in European folk medicine for treating colds and sinus issues. It reduces asphyxiation by clearing airways and boosting oxygen intake.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="WildPlantYarrow" /><GuideEntityEmbed Entity="YarrowHealingHerbs" />
[bold]Yarrow[/bold] has been used since ancient times as a hemostatic (blood-clotting) agent. It's known for its astringent properties that help staunch bleeding.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="WildPlantComfrey" /><GuideEntityEmbed Entity="ComfreyHealingHerbs" />
[bold]Comfrey[/bold] has been used historically to heal bruises, sprains, and fractures due to its anti-inflammatory and tissue-repair properties. Heals brute damage.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="WildPlantMilkThistle" /><GuideEntityEmbed Entity="MilkThistleHealingHerbs" /> [bold]Milk Thistle[/bold] has long been used as a liver tonic, with silymarin compounds believed to detoxify and protect against poisons.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="WildPlantPoppy" /><GuideEntityEmbed Entity="FoodPoppy" />[bold]Poppy[/bold] is the source of opium and morphine, known for sedative and pain-relieving effects, but it can also stabilize shock in small doses by calming the nervous system. Historically, it's been used for pain and trauma management.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="WildPlantAloe" /><GuideEntityEmbed Entity="FoodAloe" />[bold]Aloe vera[/bold]'s gel is a well-documented remedy for burns, soothing inflammation and promoting skin healing.

</Document>
